שבוע טוב Shavua tov everybody. Today's דף Daf is כ"א, Kaf Alef,
21. We pick up at the bottom of כ' עמוד ב'. Kaf
Amud Bet. We still have a little piece left before the משנה,
Mishna, about eight lines in, ten lines in, in the wide lines,
תנו רבנן. Tana Rabanan. Okay, this is finishing up the משנה Mishna
that speaks about you're not allowed to sell things connected to the
ground
to the non-Jews in Israel. Obviously raises very big questions about, well,
besides this, but also about nowadays, people using this to forbid Jews
to sell to non-Jews in Israel, and the question about really, it's
one thing when this was in the context of like a
minority group trying to hold on to their rights in the land
as opposed to when things are the reverse. In any way, so
ways of understanding this, this only applied to idolaters, only apply under
certain types of contexts. Anyway, but within that, so we had a
whole little, like, fascinating little discussion about other things about מתנת חנם,
Matnat Chinam, so sort of limited the scope of מתנת חנם, Matnat
Chinam, you know, that really it's almost always, it's never really considered
מתנת חנם, Matnat Chinam, even דרכי שלום, Darchei Shalom, other types of
reasons that it's allowed.
לא תחנם Lo Techonem was, the גמרא Gemara sort of said if
it's sort of recognizing the greatness of God's diversity of God's world,
beauty in God's world, and so on. Had a whole little digression
there about essentially about male lust. Anyway, so now we come back
to wrapping up the משנה Mishna and actually talking about this issue,
about the debate in the משנה Mishna about selling them something that's
attached to the ground on the condition that they cut it down.
Okay, so let's take a look. About eight lines down in the
wide lines on כ' עמוד ב'. Kaf Amud Bet. תנו רבנן מוכרים
אילן על מנת לקוץ וקוצץ דברי רבי יהודה. Tana Rabanan mochrim ilan
al menat likotz vekotzetz divrei Rabbi Yehuda.
Rabbi Yehuda says you can sell them a tree that's connected to
the ground on the condition that they are going to chop it
down, and and then they have to make sure that they chop
it down. That's what Rabbi Yehuda says. רבי מאיר אומר אין מוכרים
אלא קצוץ. Rabbi Meir omer ein mochrim ela katzutz. No, you can
only sell to them once it's already chopped down. Similarly, שחת על
מנת לקצור וגוזז דברי רבי יהודה. shachat al menat liktzor vegozez divrei
Rabbi Yehuda. שחת, Shachat, which is sort of like stubble, or not
exactly stubble, anyway, it's like the stuff that grows that's not yet
the wheat, it's like the stalks or whatever, and it's used for
feeding the animals. And and you can and you can cut it
down, וגוזז vegozez means he's the one, the idolater. But it presumably
the importance of having that word is that it can't be a
trick, and you have to presumably be on top of it to
make sure that it happens. רבי מאיר אומר אין מוכרים אלא
גזוזה. Rabbi Meir omer ein mochrim ela gezuza. Only if it's already
chopped down,
stubble
or whatever it is.
וגוזז Vegozez means he's the one, the idolater,
the idolater, but it presumably the importance of having that word is
that it can't be a trick, and you have to presumably be
on top of it to make sure that it happens.
קמה על מנת לקצור וקוצר דברי רבי יהודה. Kama al menat liktzor
vekotzer divrei Rabbi Yehuda. Similarly, if it's standing wheat on the condition
that he cut it down. רבי מאיר אומר אין מוכרים אלא קצורה.
Rabbi Meir omer ein mochrim ela ketzura. Only if it's already cut
down. So why do you need all three? Right? I mean just
tell me one and I can infer the others. וצריכה. Utzricha. You
need all three. דאי אשמעינן אילן בהא קאמר רבי מאיר כיון דלא
פסיד משייה ליה. De'i ashmeian ilan beha ka'amar Rabbi Meir kivan delo
pasid mashyei leih. A tree where, if the, that where, if you,
that
there you understand why Rabbi Meir is hesitant because Rabbi Meir says
look, he's
not going to lose out anything by letting the tree continue to
stand, so he'll postpone it and he'll leave it around and and
he'll have this presence in the land. אבל האי דכי משייה פסיד
ליה. Aval hai dechi mashyei pasid leih. But the case of the
שחת, shachat, if you let it continue to grow, presumably it won't
be any more fit for the animals. Okay, it won't do what
it's supposed to do. So therefore אימא מודי ליה לרבי יהודה. eima
modi leih leRabbi Yehuda. Maybe he agrees with Rabbi Yehuda that you
don't have to be concerned because obviously it's in his own interest
to cut it down quickly. ואי אשמעינן בהני תרתי. Ve'i ashmeian behani
tartei. If you just told me these two, משום דלא ידיע שבחייהו.
mishum delo yadi shuvcheihu. Because in both of those two there's no
clear benefit, meaning in the tree there's no loss leaving it around,
and in the שחת shachat there is a loss.
Maybe tree leaving it around doesn't get better?
Yeah, presumably not, I mean what, talking about a few days, whatever,
presumably there's no significant gain. Okay, so in those two there's no
real gain leaving it around. So there you understand why Rabbi Yehuda
would allow it.
אבל שחת דידיע שבחייהו. Aval shachat deyadi shuvcheihu. Wait a minute, did
I skip a line? דלא פסיד משייה ליה אבל האי דמשייה ופסיד
ליה אימא מודי ליה לרבי יהודה ואי אשמעינן בהני משום דלא ידיע
שבחייהו אבל שחת דידיע שבחייהו. Delo pasid mashyei leih aval hai demashyei
ufasid leih eima modi leih leRabbi Yehuda ve'i ashmeian behani mishum delo
yadi shuvcheihu aval shachat deyadi shuvcheihu. Wait a minute, did I
skip a line? I think I just jumped ahead to the, I
think it was the, I think I just switched the order. I
was following the order in the ברייתא, braita, but I think the
גמרא Gemara is switching the order. Okay, so
right, I'm sorry, so actually the גמרא Gemara wasn't talking about שחת
shachat yet. It was talking about the tree and the standing wheat.
Okay, so the tree and the standing wheat, the tree if you
leave it around is no gain but no loss. Okay, and there
you're afraid that he'll leave it around. Whereas the standing wheat, it
actually be a loss. I guess the wheat will start rotting if
you don't cut it in the right time. Okay, so in those
two cases you could understand A, one's the חידוש, chidush, even no
loss, the other there is a loss. Okay, but in both of
those there's no gain. So there you understand why Rabbi Yehuda would
allow it. אבל שחת דידיע שבחייהו. Aval shachat deyadi shuvcheihu. But שחת
shachat where there actually is noticeable gain if you leave it around,
אימא מודי ליה לרבי מאיר. eima modi leih leRabbi Meir. Maybe he
would agree with Rabbi Meir that you're not to be allowed to.
ואי אשמעינן בהא. Ve'i ashmeian beha. And if you just want to
just start with the שחת, shachat, דאפילו בשחת דידיע שבחייהו שרי רבי
יהודה. de'afilu beshachat deyadi shuvcheihu shari Rabbi Yehuda. That even in שחת
shachat where there's a gain leaving it around Rabbi Yehuda allows it.
בהא קאמר רבי מאיר. Beha ka'amar Rabbi Meir. That's where Rabbi Meir
doesn't allow it. אבל בהנך. Aval behanach. But in the others where
there's no gain and maybe even a loss. שחת shachas which actually
is noticeable gain if you leave it around. אימא מודי ליה לרבי
מאיר, eima modei lei le-Rebbi Meir, maybe he would agree to רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir that you are not allowed to. ואי תנא דבהא,
ve-i tanna de-beha, and if you had just start with the שחת,
shachas, that even in שחת shachas where there's a gain leaving it
around רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda allows it, because then I would say
בהא קאמר רבי מאיר, be-ha ka'amar Rebbi Meir, that's where רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir doesn't allow it, אבל בהנך, aval be-hanach, the other where
there's no gain and maybe even a loss, אימא מודי ליה לרבי
יהודה, eima modei lei le-Rebbi Yehuda, צריכא, tzricha, so you need all.
Okay, fine. ומאן דדשין בידוהי היו חייב, u-man de-dashin bi-yadov hayu chayav,
yeah,
I did that, I did read that. Okay. איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu,
now there is a question: בהמה על מנת לשחוט מהו? behema al
menat lishchot mahu? What if it's not actually a, we're not dealing
about about stuff connected to the ground and that problem, we're talking
about our other problem from the previous משנה, mishna, right? The משנה
mishna like on י"ד עמוד ב' yud daled amud beis about what
do you call it? About selling them בהמה דקה בהמה גסה. behema
daka behema gassa. Okay, and there there was a problem, I don't
know about well בהמה דקה behema daka was that whole issue, בהמה
גסה behema gassa was a שבת shabbos problem. Let's say you similarly
sold it on the condition that they slaughter it right away. Would
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda similarly allow that?
Okay, מהו? mahu? התם טעמא מאי שרי רבי יהודה דלאו ברשותיה קאי
ולא מצי משחא להו, hasam ta'ama mai sharei Rebbi Yehuda delav birshusei
ka'ei velo matzi mash'chei lehu, because maybe רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda only
allows it by the land's problem because at the end of the
day the land is your land and therefore you're in control of
it. So you could tell the guy, 'hey buddy, cut it down
or I'm just gonna go ahead and you know cut it down
myself and keep it' or whatever, meaning it's under your control, you
can more determine what gets done. אבל בהמה, aval behema, but once
you sell him the animal כיון דברשותא דעובד כוכבים קאי, keivan de-birshusa
de-oved kochavim ka'ei,
so you can make whatever conditions you want. Once you sell him
the animal it's in his home, he's gonna do what he wants
with it. So maybe you can't trust him to שחט shacht it
as as stipulated? ולא מצי משחא להו. velo matzi mash'chei lehu. הא
ברשותיה ורשותיה דעובד כוכבים קאמי משחא להו. ha birshusei u-reshusei de-oved kochavim
ka-ami mash'chei lehu. או דילמא, o dilma, do we say לא שנא,
lo shena, it won't matter? רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda in general has
a more lenient approach to these prohibitions and as long as you
stipulate, that's okay even if it's something you can't fully control the
outcome. So תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear: דתניא בהמה על
מנת לשחוט ושוחט דברי רבי יהודה. detanya behema al menat lishchot ve-shochet
divrei Rebbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda actually does allow even with
case of the animal. רבי מאיר אומר אין מוכרין לו אלא אם
כן שחוטה. Rebbi Meir omer ein mocherin lo ela im kein shechuta.
So רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda has a more lenient approach even though
you certainly understand the גמרא's Gemara question, you can't really control the
case of the בהמה, behema, but nevertheless he allows it. Okay, moving
on now as a continuing so that was so the first משנה,
mishna, like obviously you like when the משנה mishna says you can't
sell them stuff attached to the ground it's taken for granted that
you can't actually sell them real estate in the ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. So now we go we make that more explicit and we
talk about not only selling but even an issue about renting, okay
and so let's take a look. And as you could imagine this
also gets used by certain rabbis in certain religious groups in Israel
right now. אין משכירין להם בתים בארץ ישראל ואין צריך לומר שדות.
ein maskirin lahem batim be-eretz yisrael ve-ein tzarich lomar sadot. You can't
even rent them and ואין צריך לומר שדות, ve-ein tzarich lomar sadot,
excuse me, you can't even rent homes to them, okay, not let
alone sell them and you certainly can't rent fields to them. Now
why is it more obvious that you can't rent fields? What's the
whole problem altogether? So the גמרא's Gemara gonna say and I actually
have constant check the ירושלמי Yerushalmi and the ירושלמי Yerushalmi sort of
says the same thing. Anyway, it's going to say you know it's
a problem like we saw yesterday: לא תחנם חניה בקרקע. lo sechanem
chaniya be-karka.
But it's going to understand that the problem about חניה בקרקע chaniya
be-karka is only when you actually sell it to them, renting is
not is not a sufficient enough like setting down
roots. If you think by the way by אברהם, Avraham, you know
the whole story about אברהם Avraham we're going to get the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi deals with or the בבלי Bavli right now I'm over the
using track but anyway I think it's ירושלמי Yerushalmi deals with the
case about renting them a בית קברות. beis kvaros. I don't know
how you rent somebody a בית קברות. beis kvaros. You know once
somebody's buried
they're buried but anyway, but if you think about it you know
the whole story about אברהם Avraham and buying מערת המכפלה Me'aras ha-Machpela
you know from בני חת Bnei Ches and the reason the תורה
Torah goes through that whole long story of the sale and it's
such a big deal is that if you buy a burial plot
that really shows that you have permanency here right? So anyway I
mean because a burial plot is forever and also like you only
bury somebody in a place where you're setting down roots etc. So
that's why it was a big deal that אברהם Avraham was able
to buy it. But anyway but rental is not the same thing.
So the גמרא Gemara understands that rental is not this violation of
לא תחנם. lo sechanem. Now what is the difference between a house
and a field? So we're going to see that in the גמרא,
Gemara, I'll just say one word about I'll talk about it more
in the גמרא Gemara that a field in addition to the לא
תחנם lo sechanem issue is also a problem that it occasions its
status of תרומות ומעשרות. terumos u-ma'asros. Used to be stuff that would
grow there would be חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות terumos u-ma'asros now
it's not. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi says a little different. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi
says that a field is more like מתברך misbarech where a house
is not מתברך. misbarech. Meaning the field is like the source of
income whereas the house is just where you're living. And now how
does that really make a difference in terms of the prohibition about
לא תחנם? lo sechanem? Okay, so one of the מפרשים mefarshim tries
to say well when the תורה Torah says don't give them חניה,
chaniya, it means חניה chaniya that they get that they sort of
are prosperous from but I think what it also points to is
that it's not just my theory as I've been telling you that
it's not just a technical problem about well not technical but anyway
it's not just framed as a פסוק passuk about חניה בקרקע chaniya
be-karka
it's sort of a sort of a
socio a societal reality or a political reality or whatever that the
Jews are trying to ensure their presence in the ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael and they don't want to be giving up real estate. Now
if you think about it the bigger thing, you know what if
you want to maintain more if you had to weigh the two,
I mean for us we think in terms of our homes right?
But if you think about an agricultural society right the who has
the the rights to the fields right? That's means that that's like
that's real your presence more than just where you happen to be
living. So there's obviously a greater weight and greater concern like around
these issues of the field which obviously gets back you know to
all the... about the animals and the slaves and all of that
is about the you know the sense of the חזקה chazaka as
a presence and the right to it as a place of you
know in terms of the agricultural claim to the land. So anyway
so that's this and this doesn't allow you even to rent according
to this משנה. Mishna. ובסוריא U'veSurya now סוריא Surya is like sort
of I don't know if it's the same word but it's sort
of like Syria, not really, yeah, it's anyway so it's it's outside
of Israel but it was the land that was conquered by King
David and it has a different הלכה halachic status. So again if
you're being formalist in terms of the מצות לא תחנם mitzvot lo
techonem you could say it only applies maybe to ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael proper does outside of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael have the same
הלכה halacha in terms of this פסוק? pasuk? But also but if
you're looking at it not just in terms of the פסוק pasuk
but as I said in terms of sort of the societal political
reality right the Jews were much more interested I mean in maintaining
their presence in Israel proper than in some land outside of Israel
that had been conquered by King David. So we have less restrictions
in סוריא. Surya. ובסוריא משכירים להם בתים U'veSurya maskirim lahem batim you
can rent houses. It's one degree lower. In ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
you can't do anything. In סוריא Surya you can rent houses אבל
לא שדות aval lo sadot and not fields.
Fields is excuse me again more strict. Okay ובחוצה לארץ uv'chutz la'aretz
outside of Israel outside fully outside in the more far flung places
מוכרים להם בתים mochrim lahem batim one degree more lenient than that
you can even sell homes ומשכירים שדות u'maskirim sadot
and you can rent fields. But it's interesting you can't sell fields
outside of Israel like so technically if I owned a field in
Idaho I couldn't sell it to a or Iowa wherever it was
I couldn't sell it to a non-Jew like why? Like we're supposed
to maintain a presence in חוצה לארץ? chutz la'aretz? So גמרא's Gemara
clearly going to frame that as a גזירה gezeira that if you
let us do it there we'll think we can do it in
you know in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael but it's still a little
bit bizarre. I mean the חוצה לארץ chutz la'aretz of the time
of the משנה Mishna was very distant like how somebody who's going
to sell some field in בבל Bavel is going to lead to
selling a field in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael it's a little strange.
Okay unless it's only in the case of someone who owns a
field in both
places then you might say okay. That's a possibility but we don't
limit it that way. דברי רבי מאיר divrei Rabbi Meir that's what
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. That's the more strict approach. רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda who we've already seen is a more lenient. So it
says רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer where were we? דברי רבי
יוסי אומר divrei Rabbi Yossi omer excuse me it's רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi not רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yossi omer
בארץ ישראל משכירים להם בתים b'Eretz Yisrael maskirim lahem batim it's one
he starts one degree less. It's it's the same point you keep
on lowering it one level as you get further away but he
already starts more lenient in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael itself. בארץ ישראל
משכירים להם בתים אבל לא שדות B'Eretz Yisrael maskirim lahem batim aval
lo sadot you can rent homes okay you're not selling presumably selling
is only the real violation okay so we'll allow you to rent
homes but not fields. ובסוריא מוכרים להם בתים ומשכירים שדות u'veSurya mochrim
lahem batim u'maskirim sadot you always like now move everything one degree
one minute sorry. So in סוריא Surya
you can sell a home and you can rent a field okay
but don't sell a field in סוריא Surya that already makes sense
that's land directly adjacent to Israel don't sell the fields. ובחוצה לארץ
u'v'chutz la'aretz
even fully outside of Israel מוכרים אלו ואלו mochrim elu v'elu you
can sell both. Okay so thankfully we can therefore sell our fields
in in in Iowa. Okay אף במקום שאמרו
להשכיר af bimkom she'amru lehaskir last the second a next line and
this is also very important and this has real ramifications and תוספות's
Tosafot had to grapple with this. Because once you say in חוצה
לארץ chutz la'aretz you can sell whatever you want great no restrictions
but now we get this line אף במקום שאמרו להשכיר לא לבית
דירה אמרו af bimkom she'amru lehaskir lo l'veit dirah amru when you're
allowed to even rent like if you can rent maybe according to
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi you can rent a house in Israel according
to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir you can rent a house in סוריא
Surya even places you're allowed to rent you're not allowed to rent
it for a domicile. You can rent it for like a storehouse
or something but not a domicile why? מפני שמכניס לתוכו עבודה כוכבים
mipnei shemachnis l'tocho avodah kochavim because they'll bring their idols into it.
Okay let them bring their idols into it? שנאמר shenemar לא תביא
תועבה אל ביתך lo tavi toevah el beitecha don't bring an abomination
into your home. And if you're renting remember the גמרא Gemara said
before about the whole case about renting animals on שבת Shabbat that
even if you rent it's still considered to be yours right? So
you know so it actually quoted exactly this to show that it's
still yours even after you rent it. So therefore you're not allowed
to. If it's not a home then they won't bring their idols
into it but here they will and it will be considered your
home. So better to sell it to them right if you're allowed
to sell like חוצה לארץ chutz la'aretz than to rent. Okay אמרו
מפני שמכניס לתוכו עבודה כוכבים שנאמר לא תביא תועבה אל ביתך. amru
mipnei shemachnis l'tocho avodah kochavim shenemar lo tavi toevah el beitecha. ובכל
מקום לא ישכיר לו את המרחץ מפני שהוא נקרא על שמו. U'vchol
makom lo yaskir lo et hamerchatz mipnei shehu nikra al shemo. Anywhere
even in חוצה לארץ chutz la'aretz don't sell a bathhouse rent excuse
me rent a bathhouse because as long as it's not sold and
it's only still rented people will know oh it's Chaim's bathhouse and
it's operating on שבת. Shabbat. Okay here like before I told you
I was more suspicious that it was really exactly a שבת Shabbat
concern I mean I know some תנאים tannaim raised the שבת Shabbat
concern by the בהמה behema like the whole discussion around the horse
but there was a question whether that was the default reason for
the for the בהמה behema but here certainly the bathhouse is very
much seems like a type of a שבת Shabbat concern that's what
it says in the תוספתא Tosefta that's what the גמרא's Gemara going
to elaborate on. Okay so here you have this issue these other
two are different concerns. concern so תביא תועבה אל ביתך beisecha... *tavi
to'eivah el beisecha*, bathhouse is שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*, that'll be elaborated on
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but our גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is going to
focus first on the issue about renting in the Land of Israel
itself and סוריא Surya. *Suriah*, and then I remind me I want
to get back because the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* does not really discuss
the concern about bringing the idol into the rented house, but תוספות
Tosafot, *Tosfos* does. Michael's been waiting to ask a question. The previous
משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* did not explicitly mention ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael *Eretz
Yisrael* but this one does. Yeah, I mean you know it says
מחובר לקרקע *mechubar lekarka* or something, right, that's correct, that was also
taken for granted that was the locus of those previous משניות *Mishnaios*,
but that raises exactly that question as I was saying about the
whole issue about about selling you know animals, right? The גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* that makes the selling animals about a שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* concern,
you know, and I should say the ירושלמי Yerushalmi *Yerushalmi* does the
same thing, you know, then has nothing to do with being in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael*. And then תוספות Tosafot, *Tosfos* has
to deal with a whole problem about how did they sell animals,
you know, in their context? And they said, well, maybe cows and
cattle is different and all these types of issues, you know, but
but right, but base- anyway, but you know, my theory is is
that even the cattle and the animals started with an- was basically
an ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel *Eretz Yisrael* concern. But you're right, ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisroel *Eretz Yisrael* was certainly taken for granted as the
implicit context at least in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* one prior when
it spoke about מחובר לקרקע *mechubar lekarka*, and it's only being made
explicit here. Yeah, Michael. So for the house, the domicile, whatever, when
we say לא תהא דירה *lo tehei dira*, yeah, how careful do
we need to be? Like, you know, do I assume unless you
know otherwise this is a בית דירה beit dirah, *beis dira*, or
I say, alright, I'm just selling it to you, I don't care,
I don't know what you're doing, like me, I'm not specifically selling
it to you for a house. Right, that's a good question. Okay,
fine, so hold on to that when we get to discussing תוספות
Tosfot, *Tosfos* about the practical implication. There's no גמרא Gemara *Gemara* on
that, but we'll discuss תוספות Tosfot *Tosfos* in a minute and I'll
I'll try to re-address that. Let's take a look at the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*, okay? First, גמרא Gemara *Gemara* deals with the main point
of the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah*. מאי איצטריך למימר שדות *Mai itztarich lemeimar
sados*? Why is it taking for granted, why I mean why is
it necessarily renting a field, yeah, and sorry gentlemen, they reorganized, they
whatever, they cleaned up here. Why is renting a field why is
field more problematic than homes? So I already told you that the
ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* gave the more pragmatic reason of like יספרד *yispared* or
something, you know, it's really a sense of a greater sense of
your presence and prosperity in the land, but the בבלי *Bavli* here
does it more in terms of a technical concern. Okay, מאי איצטריך
למימר שדות *Mai itztarich lemeimar sados*? אי משום דאית בה תרתי *Ee
mishum de'is bah tartei*, there are two issues. What are the two
issues by field? חדא חניית קרקע *Chada haniyas karka*, what we mentioned
yesterday, a presence, a dwelling in the land, וחדא דקמפקע לה ממעשר
*vechada dekamfaka lah mimaser*, and the other is is that you can't
get status that it's not obligated in תרומות ומעשרות *trumos umasros*. אי
הכי I hachi, *Ee hachi*, says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, בתים נמי
*batim nami*, when you rent a house it changes its halakhic status,
why? אי בה תרתי *Ee bah tartei*, חדא חניית קרקע *chada haniyas
karka*, presence in the land, וחדא דקמפקע לה ממזוזה *vechada dekamfaka lah
mimzuza*, the house won't have a מזוזה mezuzah, *mezuzah* anymore. So אמר
רב משרשיא מזוזה mezuzah חובת הדר chovas hadar, הוא *Amar Rav Mesharshia
mezuzah hovas hadar hu*. No, מזוזה mezuzah *mezuzah* is an obligation of
the one who lives in it. What does that mean? How does
that make any difference? So the basic explanation, you know, that so
there's a beautiful תוספות Tosfot *Tosfos* that explains this. Basically, the point
is like this. Okay, one way is just to conceptualize it and
then think about practical. When we talk about the land, we say
the land is like חייב chayav *chayav* in תרומות ומעשרות *trumos umasros*,
and therefore when a non-Jew owns it, it's no longer חייב *chayav*
in תרומות ומעשרות *trumos umasros*. Whereas by the house, we don't say
the house is
חייב *chayav* in a מזוזה *mezuzah*, we say the owner of the
house is חייב
*chayav* in a מזוזה *mezuzah*. And if you're not like living there,
but nobody is living there, just because you have a house laying
laying by sitting by itself, right, it's like it's only obligated on
you, the one who's living there. But you know, but okay, big
deal, like, I don't know, to me that still bottom line, what's
the difference? Like, make- clarify for me how it makes sense whether
I just define it in terms of the owner or in terms
of the land. So תוספות Tosfot *Tosfos* says, fine, I'll explain it
to you. Here's the difference. Okay, if you own a house and
you're not living in it, then you don't have to put a
מזוזה *mezuzah* on it. Okay? And not only that, תוספות Tosfot *Tosfos*
suggests if I own a house and I rent it to Michael,
technically, this is a debate, but תוספות Tosfos *Tosfos* says, technically, I
am biblically- I mean rabbinically Michael has to put a מזוזה *mezuzah*
because he's the one living in it. But technically, there's no obligation
of מזוזה *mezuzah*. Why? Because it's only the obligation of ביתך beisecha,
*beisecha*. It's not Michael's בית *bayis*, it's my בית *bayis*. And it's
only the obligation of בית *bayis* when it's your house and you're
living in it. Okay? So the point that when I sell it
to a non-Jew, it's not that I change the house's status of
obligated in a מזוזה *mezuzah*. As soon as I'm not living in
the house, there's no חיוב *chiyuv* to put a מזוזה *mezuzah* there.
It's not that the non-Jew's ownership changed its status. Whereas by the
land, once a non-Jew owns the land in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel
*Eretz Yisrael*, that land has a different halakhic status, and even were
a Jew to rent the land from a non-Jew that's owned by
a non-Jew in Israel and plant the land and grow wheat, the
wheat is exempt in תרומות ומעשרות *trumos umasros*. Okay, that's a debate
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* whether יש קנין לעכו"ם *yesh kinyan l'akum*
you know to להפקיעה מתרומה ומעשר *lehafki'ah mi-terumah u-ma'aser* to change the
land status you know in terms of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel *Eretz
Yisrael*. But תוספות Tosfos, *Tosfos* is saying this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
assuming that it does. So there really is a difference. In one
case, it's not that the house is obligated and the ownership of
a non-Jew changed the status, it's just I am obligated to put
a מזוזה *mezuzah* in my house when I am living in it.
If I am not living in it, the house can sit around
without a מזוזה *mezuzah*. Whereas the land has a status of קדושת
ארץ ישראל Kedushat Eretz Yisroel, *kedushas Eretz Yisrael* that leads to the
fact that the grain that comes from it is חייב *chayav*. from
a non-Jew and plants in it, it would remain exempt from תרומות
ומעשרות. Yes, which is by the way, when, when do we regularly
rent the land from non-Jews and get out of its halakhic status?
שמיטה. Shmita. We sell the whole land. All right. So we sell
basically all of Israel, then we grow in it, and we're exempt.
So it's the ownership of the non-Jew changes its הלכה halacha status.
So that's why it's seen as more weighty. So this is on
a purely like הלכה מצוה halacha mitzvah basis, not on the as
I said, the sort of presence in the land of Israel basis.
Yes, David. Wait, so you have to own the house and live
in it, right? According to תוספות, Tosfos it's because of the combination
of ביתך... beitecha oh my god, I can't believe it. Spilled my
thermos and which I really could use and I left it at
home. Okay, anyway, the combination of... no, it's all right, it's all
right, I've already... yeah, the combination of ביתך, beitecha, of your house,
and the fact that it's when you're living in your house. Now
some might disagree. Some might say that if you rent a house,
even though we just had a whole discussion that rental is not
like ownership, but since by the מזוזה, the focus is what the
גמרא Gemara, says חובת הדר, the obligation of the one who lives
in it, maybe for מזוזה purposes
it is considered to be enough your house. Okay, so that's actually
a question, but according to תוספות, Tosfos if you're not living in
somebody else's rent, even if the renter is a Jew, you're rabbinically
obligated but you're not biblically obligated.
The reason I ask is because I'm renting an apartment, but I
don't own the apartment. Right, that is true. So rabbinically you're obligated,
but not biblically. Yes, Charlie. So I see מזוזות mezuzos on retail
stores, office buildings, nobody's living in these places. Right, so that is
not halakhically obligated. That is just because, you know, some people do
it because of good luck or whatever, in some cases it's supposed
like whatever, you know, anyway, yes, okay, but anyway, yeah, okay, hold
on, I'm sorry, just asking her to bring me my thermos if
she can, because that's something very important. What? Yes, coffee is extremely
important, exactly. All right, anyway, somebody's just showing me they're reading a
book about Jews and coffee. Anyway, all right, so now let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara Okay, so that's the difference between
land and between field and a home. בסוריא משכירין בתים. BeSurya maskirin
batim. Okay, now what's now we deal with סוריא. Surya סוריא Surya
is one degree less serious, less severe than Israel in terms of
this. מאי שנא מכירה דלא? Mai shna mechira d'lo? Now why in
סוריא Surya even in סוריא Surya? can you not sell a house
according to רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? משום מכירה דארץ ישראל, Mishum mechira
d'Eretz Yisrael, because presumably the only thing that's actually prohibited is selling
and doing it in Israel itself. אי הכי, if that's true, says
the גמרא, Gemara, משכירות נמי נגזור, mischirus nami nigzor, so why don't
we prohibit even renting in סוריא? Surya, If we prohibited renting in
Israel, let's prohibit renting in סוריא, Surya, that'll lead to renting in
Israel. So the גמרא Gemara says, היא גופא גזירה ואנן נקומה ונגזור
גזירה לגזירה? hi gufa gezeira ve'anan nekuma venigzor gezeira ligezeira? What, it
itself is a safeguard, renting in Israel, because renting in Israel, the
real problem is sale. So now we should make a safeguard to
a safeguard? Even in Israel, the only reason you don't rent is
because it'll lead to selling, so in סוריא, Surya? which is one
degree removed, we can allow renting. So the גמרא Gemara, says, גזירה
לגזירה והא שכירות שדה? gezeira ligezeira v'ha schirus sadeh? But one minute,
renting a field, you don't allow in סוריא? Surya דבסוריא דגזירה לגזירה
היא, debiSurya d'gezeira ligezeira hi, right? Even in סוריא Surya according to
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, you only allow renting a house, you don't
allow renting a field. But even renting a field in Israel is
only a safeguard, so that's two degrees removed, והא קא גזרינן? v'ha
ka gazrinan? So the גמרא Gemara says, no, התם לאו גזירה היא.
hatam lav gezeira hi. Actually, the renting of the field in סוריא
Surya is not a גזירה לגזירה. gezeira ligezeira. Why? Or סוריא Surya
is not a גזירה. gezeira. סוריא Surya is itself like Israel. קסבר,
Kasavar, the author of this תנא, Tanna, meaning רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
is of the position that כיבוש יחיד שמה כיבוש, kibush yachid shmei
kibush, that actually the conquering of an individual of דוד המלך, David
HaMelech, I'll get to a minute, a discussion in a minute why
this is called כיבוש יחיד, kibush yachid, but it means that fact
that דוד David conquered סוריא Surya is considered to actually make it
considered like to legitimately, you know, make it an annexation of Israel.
שמה כיבוש. Shmei kibush. So שדה דאית בה תרתי. sadeh d'is bei
tartei. So therefore סוריא Surya? is really just like Israel halakhically. Of
course it's not exactly like Israel, because even the משנה Mishnah shows
a difference. So what it's saying is, okay, but so rabbinically, since
it's not ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel proper, which is a little funny,
because if technically it was all really just about the מצוה mitzvah
of לא תחנם, Lo Sechanem, then and the מצוה mitzvah of לא
תחנם Lo Sechanem applied equally in both places, why wouldn't we be
making any distinction? So clearly there's some other factor other than לא
תחנם. Lo Sechanem. And again, so maybe here subtly the גמרא Gemara
is sort of recognizing at the end that idea there are other
things going on, like where's the עיקר ישוב ikar yishuv of בני
ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, where do we want to work harder to sustain,
you know, whatever, of the Jewish people, where do we want to
work harder to sustain that and so on. So what it says
is, okay. The thing is ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael* and
סוריא Surya? *Surya* according to Rabbi Meir are equally ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael* for the הלכות *halachos* of לא תחנם *lo sechanem*.
Okay, but rabbinically we're going to be stricter in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael* proper. Okay, so in ארץ ישראל Yisrael, *Eretz Yisrael*
proper we don't allow anything. In סוריא *Surya*, even though that's a
little harsher, right? 'Cause it's only cause but okay, we don't allow
anything. In סוריא *Surya*, okay, we're going to allow renting of houses.
It's true, were you to sell a house in סוריא *Surya*, that
would be a biblical violation according to this. סוריא *Surya* is just
like ארץ ישראל Yisrael, *Eretz Yisrael*. That would be a problem of
לא תחנם *lo sechanem*. But you know what? Since it's not ארץ
ישראל Israel, *Eretz Yisrael* proper, we're going to go easy on some
of the rabbinic safeguards. We'll make a rabbinic safeguard by fields, which
are weightier, but not by homes. Okay. So שדה דאית בה תרתי
*sadeh de-is bei tartei*, שדה *sadeh* has two things, גזרו בה רבנן
*gazru bei rabbanan*. We make a safeguard, okay. But בבתים דליכא תרתי
*bbatim deleika tartei*, בבתים *bbatim* only has one issue, חניה *chanayah*, but
it doesn't have this קדושת ארץ ישראל Kedushat Eretz Yisroel, *kedushas Eretz
Yisrael* for תרומות ומעשרות *trumos u-maasros*, so לא גזרו בה רבנן *lo
gazru bei rabbanan*, which is interesting. I mean, okay, but there's a
biblical thing, but you know what? We don't always feel the need
to make safeguards. So סוריא *Surya* is like ארץ ישראל Israel, *Eretz
Yisrael*, but it's not ארץ ישראל Israel. *Eretz Yisrael* proper at the
end of the day.
And therefore, we basically we go easy on one thing. We don't
make a safeguard by homes.
We let you rent homes, but not sell them. We don't have
the need to make a safeguard. And in חוץ לארץ Chutz La’aretz
*Chutz La'aretz*, we go one degree less than that. We let you
sell homes and we let you rent fields, but not sell fields.
בחוץ לארץ שדה דאית בה תרתי *be-Chutz La'aretz sadeh de-is bei tartei*,
same point, גזרו בה רבנן *gazru bei rabbanan*. So in the fields
outside of Israel, we... it's not a safeguard... it's a safeguard that
if we let you sell fields outside of Israel, you'll come to
sell fields in Israel. Seems pretty far-fetched, but that's the concern. So
fields, which is always the weightiest thing, we maintain the גזרה *gezeirah*
even fully outside Israel. בתים דליכא תרתי *battim deleika tartei*, בתים *battim*
that don't have a, you know, two problems, לא גזרו בה רבנן
*lo gazru bei rabbanan*, there we actually let you directly buy homes
outside of Israel... I mean sell homes outside of Israel and we're
not afraid that it'll lead to you...
I mean
sell homes outside of Israel and we're not afraid that it'll lead
to you selling homes in the Land of Israel. Okay, so that's
basically we make different
degrees of safeguard, but it's all because by fundamentally, at least halakhically,
this is saying סוריא *Surya* is considered part of ארץ ישראל *Eretz
Yisrael*.
Let's finish Rabbi Yose, the other position, then we'll go back and
discuss about כיבוש יחיד kivush yachid *kibbush yachid* and the other things
that are going on here. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi אומר בארץ ישראל
משכירים להם בתים *Rabbi Yose omer be-Eretz Yisrael maskirim lahem battim*, מאי
טעמא Mai Ta'ama? *mai ta'ama*, so Rabbi Yose allows you already in
Israel one degree... like he already allows a certain leniency. You can
rent homes. Which means, presumably, that he's not going to make a
safeguard against homes about... he's not going to be afraid you're going
to sell homes even in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* proper. מאי טעמא
שדה דאית בה תרתי גזרו רבנן בתים דליכא תרתי לא גזרו בה
רבנן *mai ta'ama sadeh de-is bei tartei gazru rabbanan battim deleika tartei
lo gazru bei rabbanan*, similar to what Rabbi Meir said by סוריא
*Surya*. But Rabbi Yose is saying like, look, I just go more
lenient here. I think maybe it's also realistically you can't prevent people
from trying to rent their homes and so on, people have to,
you know, go ahead and live or whatever they... you know, they
have to... whatever, this is an important part of the economy. So
even so anyway, in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* itself, at least I
will allow renting homes, I'm not going to feel the need to
make a safeguard. Okay, fields I won't let you rent because I'm
afraid it'll lead to selling. ובסוריא מוכרים *u-ve-Surya mocherim*, in סוריא *Surya*
you can sell homes. And now here comes the real basis of
a difference also. If he allows you to sell homes in סוריא
*Surya*, that means he's not treating סוריא *Surya* as ארץ ישראל *Eretz
Yisrael*, because if he were, because anywhere you're allowed to sell, clearly
it can't be ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. So מאי טעמא קסבר כיבוש
יחיד kivush yachid לא שמיה כיבוש *mai ta'ama kasavar kibbush yachid lo
shemei kibbush*. That conquering of סוריא *Surya* is not considered really annexed
to ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, and it does not really have an
ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* status. So therefore, you allow selling of homes,
the only way you could allow selling of homes if it's not
ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* proper, and you allow the renting of fields.
ושדה דאית בה תרתי גזרו בה רבנן *ve-sadeh de-is bei tartei gazru
bei rabbanan*. So we didn't allow the selling of fields there, we
made a safeguard, we only allowed the renting of fields, because we're
going to make a safeguard against doing it in Israel. Okay, בתים
דליכא תרתי לא גזרו בה רבנן *battim deleika tartei lo gazru bei
rabbanan*, but the homes we basically totally allowed. Go sell homes, we're
not afraid that that's going to lead, if we allow you to
sell homes in סוריא *Surya*, we're not afraid it's going to lead
to selling homes in the Land of Israel. ובחוץ לארץ מוכרים *u-ve-Chutz
La'aretz mocherim*, in חוץ לארץ Chutz La’aretz *Chutz La'aretz* you can sell
everything. מאי טעמא *mai ta'ama*, why? כיון דמרחק לא גזרינן *keivan demirchak
lo gazrinan*, since it's very distant, we're obviously not concerned that any
even selling fields will lead to anything. Okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל הלכה כרבי יוסי *amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel halacha ke-Rabbi Yose*.
We rule like Rabbi Yose, which is nice, which means that we
can go ahead and sell homes and fields outside of Israel, and
even in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* at least we can rent homes.
אמר רב יוסף Amar Rav Yosef *amar Rav Yosef*, ובלבד שלא יעשנו
שכונה u'vilvad shelo ya'asenu shchuna. *u-vilvad shelo yaasenu shechunah*. Now we get
to something which also shows very clear, because we're talking here in
full חוץ לארץ Chutz La’aretz. *Chutz La'aretz*, that we're not just concerned
about issues about גזרות *gezeiros* and לא תחנם *lo sechanem*, we're concerned
about other realities about Jewish neighborhoods. Okay, yes, you can go ahead
and rent and sell a home in your... you know, what... what
did they used to be called, this is how they kept the
Jews out, covenants or what... what was that called? Restrictive covenants. Restrictive
covenants, like in a certain neighborhood we're not going to allow Jews
or blacks, nobody can sell their home to Jews... my grandparents bought
a house with that stipulation. Right. There were places much later than
that. I'm sure. It doesn't mean that it was legal. Is it
going to be between all of us or you? No, no, no,
shh, I'll get to it. Anyways, so anyway, that's very interesting, right,
when you see it from the other side. Right, it's usually the
Jews who are excluded. I do have to tell you that this
is something I've found very interesting talking to Israelis, because I don't
know if anybody ever knows, but in Israel, I don't think this
applies in like cities, like in ירושלים or whatever, but in like
ישובים yishuvim or whatnot, they, they decide who gets to live there.
You know, acceptance boards. And you know, if you want to come
and move into, and some of them do not allow people that
are not דתי, dati, that's clear. You know, some of them, whatever.
I mean, you know, I will tell you that my, I have
a nephew who because he's totally very פרום, frum, his wife super
פרום, frum, whatever. Anyway, but because they ideologically don't like the רבנות
rabbanut or whatever, they refuse to get married according to like the
רבנות, rabbanut, you know. So they have a status of like מוכר
בציבור mukar batzibur or something like that, you know. Anyway, whatever it
is. Anyway, so they, the, the, the neighborhood they wanted to move
into, which was this דתי, dati, you know, ישוב, yishuv, first didn't
want to let them move into there because they weren't הלכתית halachically
married. So you know, they didn't want, they didn't want people living
in sin, you know. Obviously they were totally פרום frum whatever. No,
they were הלכתית halachically because they weren't רבנות rabbanut married, they weren't
state married. Anyway, whatever. Okay, so, so this idea, right? I mean,
it's an interesting question right about individual rights versus communitarian values. Right,
you know, there is an idea of a character to a neighborhood.
The problem is when it leads to exclusion, you know, how does
that rub up against, you know, that sense of rights and so
on? So anyway, so here the shoe is on the other foot.
We were excluding the non-Jew from our neighborhood. We wanted it to
remain a nice good Jewish neighborhood. So you can sell them maybe
some homes, but don't sell them enough that you create a little
mini non-Jewish neighborhood in your neighborhood. Okay? One minute. Well, yeah, well
everybody polices themselves. אמר רב יוסף ובלבד שלא יעשנו שכונה. shechunah, Don't
turn that into a little neighborhood. כמה שכונה? Kama shchuna? How much
would that be? כמה אין שכונה פחותה משלושה בני אדם? Kama ein
shchuna p'chuta mishlosha b'nei adam? Three people. Okay? Don't sell to, yeah,
presumably he means three households. That's a good question. I assumed it
meant three households. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says וליחוש דילמא אזיל
האי ישראל ומזבין לחד וביתא להאי. v'leichosh dilma azil hai Yisrael u'mazbin
l'chad u'veita l'hai. You're going to go sell to one non-Jew, ואזיל
האי ומזבין ליה לתרי, v'azil hai u'mazvin lei l'trei, and this guy
is going to subdivide his home and sell it to two other
families and he'll keep a part of the home for himself and
then there'll be three non-Jews in your neighborhood, three non-Jewish families. אמר
אביי Amar Abaye אלפני מפקדינן אלפני דלפני לא מפקדינן. a'lifnei mifakdinan a'lifnei
dilifnei lo mifakdinan. That was an earlier אביי. Abaye. תוספות, Tosfos רש"י,
Rashi, תוספות Tosfos say this is לאו דווקא. lav davka. We're not
afraid of לפני lifnei either. But what it means is like two
degrees removed we're not afraid. Okay? We're only preventing you from directly
selling it. Now of course Michael makes a good point, but if
Michael sold to one non-Jewish family, can everybody sell to one or
that means like, no, in the whole neighborhood we can't have more
than three non-Jews. So like, you know, if you get to be
the first two families to sell to non-Jews, then everybody else is
not allowed. And then everyone else needs to figure out how a
religious house is going to work. Right. Exactly. So I don't exactly
know, but it is very interesting and you know, it's a little
bit of like eye opening, you know, to see this from the
other side of the equation. Not like the non-Jews were ever the
discriminated-against class, but to sort of see this issue about like trying
to maintain this identity of a neighborhood. You certainly I think can
be more sympathetic when the people that are trying to maintain it
are the minority class who's oppressed from the others and are trying
to, you know, hold on to their identity in the presence of
a much larger society. Anyway, let me talk say two things now
about, both first about the point about כיבוש יחיד kivush yachid and
then about the issue about about what do you call it, about
the renting the homes and how that applied in contemporary times, post
גמרא Gemara times. So the כיבוש יחיד Kibbush Yachid. issue, רש"י Rashi
says that כיבוש יחיד is, is that דוד המלך David Hamelech did
it without the authority of the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. Okay? He just did
it on, he waged his own wars and therefore he was acting
on his own. And he also says without like שישים ריבו. shishim
ribo. The idea that six hundred thousand represents בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael.
Does that mean you need to have six hundred thousand people in
your army or does that mean that somehow you're seen as representing,
you know, you did some type of a plebiscite or whatever it
was, you know, referendum? But anyway for רש"י Rashi the idea is,
is it a king waging his private war or is he representing
the people? And if the land that was conquered was not conquered
as a representative of the entire nation, then it does not become
the land of ישראל, the land of the people of ישראל, because
it was a land conquered by an ישראל, a king of ישראל,
but not by the people of ישראל. Okay? So that's רש"י, Rashi,
that makes a lot of sense. תוספות Tosfos quotes a ספרי Sifrei
and תוספות Tosfos sort of makes it a little bit more, I
don't know like, I don't know what I would say, formalistic or
whatever, but תוספות Tosfos says the following: the point was was that
דוד David waged these wars before ארץ ישראל proper had been fully
conquered. And the conceptually the idea is that you can only have
an extension of the Land of Israel if it builds on ארץ
ישראל proper. But before ארץ ישראל proper had finished being conquered, okay,
then this is not seen, cannot build on the base. You need
the base for it to build on. So the extension of קדושת
ארץ ישראל, obviously what had already been conquered in ארץ ישראל had
קדושת ארץ ישראל, okay, but the concept that you could extend beyond
is you have to first, like you know, finish the base work
before you can go beyond that. And therefore there was something inherently
illegitimate. Stop worrying about these other lands, it's almost like why are
you not prioritizing Israel? Is this just about land conquering or is
it about the land, you know, about the Land of Israel that
God had given you? So the fact that you're going and concerned
about other lands and not about this land itself, that makes that
fundamentally like not legitimate and therefore certainly something that you can't extend
the קדושה Kedushah of ארץ ישראל to that. So that's the issues
about כיבוש יחיד. Interesting debate of רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosfos on
that. Let me talk a little bit about the issue about renting
homes. So of course to look at this תוספות, Tosfos אף מקום
שאמרו להשכיר לא לבית דירה אמרו, Af makom she’amru lehaskir lo l’veit
dirah amru, that big תוספות Tosfos at the bottom, okay, so תוספות
Tosfos says the following. He says, יש לפקפק, Yeish l’fakpek, we can
like raise the question, על מה היו סומכים בני אדם למכור ולהשכיר
בתים לעובדי כוכבים? Al mah hayu somchim bnei adam limkor u’lehaskir batim
l’ovdei kochavim? On what basis do we nowadays sell and rent homes
to non-Jews? Now selling it isn't a problem, well unless it's selling
three homes and then it's a שכונה, but renting, how do we
rent? Okay, and even for a בית דירה, okay, and we even
rent them for for places of domicile. Okay. And then he goes
to a couple of different possibilities. One is that, well let's read
a little bit. ויש רוצים להביא ראיה להתיר מדתני בתוספתא, V’yeish rotzim
l’havi ra’ayah l’hatir midtani b’Tosefta, כאן וכאן לא ישכור אדם ביתו לעובד
כוכבים, Kan v’kan lo yaskir adam beito l’oved kochavim, don't rent your
house, מפני שידוע שמכניס לתוכו עבודה זרה. mipnei sheyaduah shemachnis l’tocho avodah
zarah. אלו הן כאן וכאן? Elu hen kan v’kan? ארץ ישראל or
סוריא? חוץ לארץ Chutz La’aretz or סוריא? מפני שידוע שמכניס לתוכו עבודה
זרה. mipnei sheyaduah shemachnis l’tocho avodah zarah. He brings in an idol.
אפילו הכי, Afilu hachi, says the תוספתא, Tosefta, משכירים להם אורוות ואוצרות
ופונדקאות, maskirim lahem urvot v’otzarot u’fundakaot, you sell them all these other
types of places, inns and and barns, etc. And now תוספות Tosfos,
explains, this next point is not in the תוספתא, Tosefta, אף על
פי שידוע שמכניס לתוכו עבודה זרה. af al pi sheyaduah shemachnis l’tocho
avodah zarah. I'm not, it is in תוספתא, Tosefta, I'm sorry. אף
על פי שידוע שמכניס לתוכו עבודה זרה, Af al pi sheyaduah shemachnis
l’tocho avodah zarah, even though you know they're bringing in idols. I
don't, okay. So there are some places you can rent even though
you know they bring in idols. So what's the story? Why is
it allowed if you know they bring in idols? So תוספות Tosfos
says משמע טעמא משום שמחלק בין מקום שמכניס עבודה זרה בקביעות בין
שאינו מכניס. mashma ta’ama mishum shemechalek bein makom shemachnis avodah zarah bikviut
bein she’eino machnis. So תוספות Tosfos stipulates, or not stipulates, תוספות Tosfos
hypothesizes that the difference is whether you keep your idol in your
home, that's a problem, or whether you just bring it in temporarily.
If you're staying in an inn, you might bring your idol in
temporarily, but you're not, for the night, but you're not bringing it
in permanently. And if that's the difference, תוספות Tosfos says, then maybe
we can say nowadays the non-Jews we rent to, they don't actually
keep keep their like, you know, icons or whatever, their statues in
their home on a permanent basis. And that's what he says. והשתא
עובדי כוכבים שבינינו אינם מכניסים לבתיהם עבודה זרה בקביעות. V’hashta ovdei kochavim
shebeineinu einam machnisim l’vateihem avodah zarah bikviut. The non-Jews among us, they
don't bring their like little statues or whatever into their homes on
a regular basis. אלא כשיש מת, Ela k’sheyeish meit, if somebody is
is has died, או שנוטה למות, o shenoteh lamut, or somebody's on
their deathbed, interesting little insight into that reality, וגם אותה שעה אינם
עובדים אותם, v’gam otah sha’ah einam ovdim otam, and even then they
just bring it in, I don't know, for the for the protection
that it brings, but they don't actually do an act of worship
towards it, מותר, mutar, it's permissible. So one explanation is it's only
if they bring in their icons like in a permanent basis. And
then they're worshipping it constantly. What can I tell you? Anyway, that's
one answer. But then תוספות Tosafos, says, but the then תוספות Tosafos
says, but you know what, that might not be the פשט pshat
in the תוספתא. Tosefta. The פשט pshat in the תוספתא Tosefta might
be לא תביא תועבה אל ביתך, Lo tavi to’evah el beitecha, that
ביתך beitecha means a home that you actually live in, not an
inn and not a barn, etc. So then that would and it
has nothing to do with permanent or temporary. And then that wouldn't
help because we still rent out our homes, our real ביתך, beitecha?
our real domiciles, we rent them to non-Jews. So what's the explanation?
So then תוספות Tosafos. says, four lines from the bottom, ורבינו חיים
כהן, v’Rabbeinu Chaim Kohen, רבינו חיים כהן, Rabbeinu Chaim Kohen, היה מביא
ראיה להתיר מדילפינן בירושלמי אף מקום שאמרו להשכיר לא לבית דירה אמרו
הא במקום שנהגו למכור מוכר אף לבית דירה ומשכיר אף לבית דירה.
hayah meivi ra’ayah l’hatir midyalfinan b’Yerushalmi af makom she’amru lehaskir lo l’veit
dirah amru ha b’makom shenahagu limkor mocher af l’veit dirah u’maskir af
l’veit dirah. So he tries to bring a proof from the ירושלמי
that it is permissible to rent. But what's the logic? What's the
problem? What about לא תביא תועבה אל ביתך? Lo tavi to’evah el
beitecha? So he says, here's the logic: ויש לומר דבחוץ לארץ לא
מיקרי ביתך אלא בארץ. V’yeish lomar d’b’chutz la’aretz lo mikrei beitecha ela
ba’aretz. So here's a nice good Zionist claim. Even a home that
you own in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz is not your real home.
Your real home, like you know, don't they have that sign when
you like land in Ben-Gurion like 'Welcome Home' or something like that?
You know, your real home is always Israel. So therefore, it's never
a ביתך beitecha in חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz So תוספות Tosafos says,
really? You mean I’m like never חייב in a מזוזה in חוץ
לארץ because it's never ביתך? beitecha. Okay, and then let me just
try to remember the the final answer תוס Tos gives. Oh, the
final answer תוס Tos gives is that it's only ביתך according to
the דאורייתא d'oraita if you're living in the home. If you rent
the home and you're not living there, that might not be ביתך.
So maybe, so the גמרא Gemara is מדרבנן mid'rabonon an extension of
it. So תוס Tos tries to justify why they rent the homes
because תוס Tos basically says three possibilities: either they don't bring it
in permanently or it's not your home because anything in חוץ לארץ
isn't really your home. Okay, that's cute. Or the תורה Torah only
forbids it when you're actually there living there and you went in
while you remain living there. But if you don't remain living there—I
live in like the top floor—exactly, exactly. But if you don't remain
living there, then it is not biblical and it's only דרבנן, rabonon,
then we can find ways to allow given, you know, there's more
to negotiate. But once again, the regular theme that we've been seeing
this tractate which is that in תוס Tos's time they tried to
both treat Christianity as עבודה זרה avoda zara and then had this
constant ways in which their practice was running up against these restrictions.
This continues even to the time of the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch
and the רמ"א. Rama. Some try to explain that you know I
told you that this attitude develops that that that that you know
Christianity it's not עבודה זרה avoda zara for non-Jews, it's עבודה זרה
avoda zara for Jews. So then the question is can we then
use that to explain to allow us to rent houses? And the
answer was still like no, because that still has to be from
our definition. So from our definition it's still עבודה זרה. avoda zara.
It doesn't matter that from their definition it's not. So then the
answer was well maybe they're not really sincere about their worshipping of
their עבודה זרה. avoda zara. It doesn't matter if they're bringing their
images into their home, right, you know, their statues or whatever. So
this really continued to be a discussion well into like the 17th
century and whatever about how they rent homes to Christians who then
go ahead and bring their like various icons and statues into their
home. That's odd. No, it's just whatever, they're trying to reconcile. Anyway,
so let's take a look now. Now we continue, okay. אף מקום
שהתירו להשכיר, Af makom shehitiru lehaskir, even places you're allowed to rent
you can't rent for a, you know, for a domicile. מכלל, Miklal,
says the גמרא, דאיכא דוכתא דלא מוגרי. d'ika duchteh d'la mogri. Hi,
you thought we weren't going to finish the דף daf today. Okay,
there are places where it sounds like there's some places you can
rent, some places you can't rent. וסתמא רבי מאיר, Ustama Rabbi Meir,
that's going like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, cause רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says in ארץ ישראל you can't rent a home. דאי רבי יוסי
בכל דוכתא מוגרי, D'ee Rabbi Yossi bechol duchteh mogri, because רבי יוסי
even allows in ארץ ישראל to rent a home. So anyway the
last part of the משנה Mishnah that implies there are places you
can't rent homes is like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Fine, but the
larger point is don't rent a home even in places where it's
allowed for a domicile because they'll bring their עבודה זרה avoda zara
into it. And then you get to, but in no place can
you rent a bathhouse because then... or you can sell a bathhouse
but don't rent it because it'll be operated on שבת Shabbat and
people will think look, Dov is running his bathhouse operation on שבת
Shabbat. and he's having non-Jews heat up the water and he's collecting
the fees and whatever because it's still Dov's bathhouse. So they don't
know that I rented it and the non-Jew is doing it operating
on his own and keeping all the profits. So that really looks
bad, so I'm not allowed to do that. Okay, so the גמרא
says what? That seems like it would happen today with people who
rent their stores. Right, so let's take a look exactly. So let's
take a look at the גמרא, okay? And then that's why there's
this huge תוס Tos as well. Okay, so let's take a look.
תניא, Tanya, תנא ברייתא, tana braita, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel omer, לא ישכור אדם מרחצו לעובד כוכבים, lo yaskir
adam merchatzu l'oved kochavim, do not rent your bathhouse to a non-Jew,
מפני שנקרא שמו, mipnei shenikra shemo, because it's still known as yours,
ועובד כוכבים זה עושה בו מלאכה בשבת ובימים טובים, v'oved kochavim zeh
oseh bo melacha b'Shabbat u'b'Yomim Tovim, and he operates it on שבת
Shabbos. and יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay, so the גמרא says אבל
לכותים מאי שרי? aval l'Kutim mai shari? So it sounds like it's
only not acceptable to a non-Jew, sounds like it would be okay
to rent it to a Samaritan because that keeps coming up here
in the תוספתא, Tosefta, it's very, it's very consistent, it's always addressing
the issue of a Samaritan. Oh, but it still has כותי. Kuti.
Fine. Well, it is כותי Kuti here. This is not a censor,
this is
literally כותי. Kuti. אימא עבדי במלאכה בחולו של מועד, Eima avdei b'melacha
b'cholo shel moed, so we know that a כותי Kuti is okay
because a כותי Kuti won't operate it on שבת. Shabbos But one
minute, says the גמרא, כותים Kutim don't believe in an איסור מלאכה
issur melacha בחולו של מועד, b'cholo shel moed, so why aren't we
concerned that they'll operate it on חולו של מועד? cholo shel moed?
What's the problem taking bath? Ah. So the גמרא says בחולו של
מועד אנן נמי עבדינן, becholo shel moed anan nami avdinan, we also
can heat up water for a bath on חולו של מועד. cholo
shel moed. What's the problem? שכוח Shkoach Michael. Okay, also the גמרא
says fine. אבל שדה לעובד כוכבים מאי שרי. Aval sadeh l'oved kochavim
mai shari. Now it sounds like the only issue is renting a
bathhouse. Renting a field you're allowed to do, right? That was pretty
explicit from the משנה. The משנה had issues about renting a field
in ארץ ישראל and סוריה, Suriya, whatever, but in חוץ לארץ you
can rent a field, right? So now one minute. Why? If it's
still known as my field and they see him working in it,
right? So Dennis's question, people will assume that I hired him to
work my field on שבת. Shabbos, So מאי טעמא? אריסותא אריסותיה קעבדי
Arisuta arisuteih kavdi because people will understand no, it's very standard that
by fields sometimes you have hired hands by fields, but a very
standard way of arrangement by fields is sharecropping. So people who see
a non-Jew working in my field on שבת Shabbos, will take it
for granted that he's a sharecropper. And as a sharecropper even though
I benefit from the profits, he is operating on his own schedule,
on his own calendar. I am not telling him what to do.
So therefore since people obviously I can't hire him to work my
field on שבת, Shabbos, but I can rent my field to him,
I can have a sharecropper arrangement and we assume that people will
see it through the right lens. So the גמרא says if that's
true, מרחץ נמי אמרי אריסותא אריסותיה קעבדי, Merchatz nami amri arisuta arisuteih
kavdi, so why don't people assume the same by a bathhouse? They'll
assume they've rented it or they did a profit-sharing arrangement with this
non-Jew, and he's not telling the non-Jew to work on שבת, Shabbos.
the non-Jew is making his own decisions. So the גמרא says no,
אריסותא דמרחץ לא עבדי אינשי, Arisuta de-merchatz lo avdi inish, people usually
do not do profit-sharing arrangements of a bathhouse is so profitable, I'm
going to hire the workers and keep the profits myself. I'm not
going to go ahead so therefore since people will not read it
through the proper lens, they will assume that I have hired these
workers to work on שבת, Shabbos, not that they've rented it or
it's profit-sharing, that's why it's not allowed. Now I'm going to I
want to just stop here and say something about this תוספות, Tosafos
we won't you know we'll continue the next line tomorrow. But here's
the thing, first of all there's two questions to ask. One is
it's a little funny that it's like a מראית עין Maris Ayin
for a דרבנן, De-rabonon, right? What are we afraid? People will see
them working it and they'll suspect that I hired them to work
it on on שבת. Shabbos. But if I hired a non-Jew to
work my bathhouse on שבת, Shabbos it's only a rabbinic violation of
אמירה לעכו"ם. Amira l'akum. So we're so concerned about a מראית עין
Maris Ayin for a דרבנן? De-rabonon? So the answer might be yes,
sometimes we are concerned for מראית עין Maris Ayin for a דרבנן,
De-rabonon, but the bigger answer is how this violates the community's the
sense that we are communally observing שבת. Shabbos, It's not just they'll
think oh Dov violated some איסור דרבנן, Issur de-rabonon, it's that they
see a bathhouse running and the way that's experienced by the community
is Dov's bathhouse is open for business on שבת Shabbos. and Dov
is running his bathhouse on שבת, Shabbos right? That's not just suspecting
me of doing some technical איסור. Issur. That's like a violating of
the whole that's almost like you know מחלל שבת בפרהסיא, Mechalel Shabbos
be-farhesya, like a violate in the public space the sense that a
Jewish enterprise is up and running on שבת. Shabbos That seems to
me to be the bigger issue as opposed to if it's understood
that it's sharecropping or whatever, that's just not how it's experienced in
a different way. So that's the first point I wanted to make
that it's not just a דרבנן De-rabonon issue. Okay, of a מראית
עין Maris Ayin issue. Now the bigger question becomes about how does
this translate into other concerns, right? You know like you have in
a היתר מכירה Heter Mechira and you sell your company to a
non-Jew and you do these types of things right whatever it is
or you have right? So a there's enterprise there are business enterprises,
you know and again presumably once the arrangements become well enough established
you know that people understand that that's what you do, you sell
your whole you know your business to a non-Jew and for שבת
Shabbos. and they work it on שבת Shabbos or whatever the case
might be. But that's a question, but the bigger question that תוספות
deals with and this comes up also all the time is then
I'm having a house built and they want to continue working on
it on שבת. Shabbos, Right? Or you know how about like I
just got this question like a week ago, like my what do
you call it? My pipes got clogged you know whatever it's ערב
שבת, Erev Shabbos, the plumber finally has shown up, if he doesn't
if I don't let him work starting now like an hour before
שבת Shabbos and he's going to go three hours into שבת, Shabbos
I'm going to have to move out of the house for שבת
Shabbos because we're basically not going to have any water on שבת
Shabbos, and the whole thing, right? You know what do you do
in those cases? Last ערב שבת Erev Shabbos Devorah's house was smelling
gas. It wasn't, they were painting downstairs. But like you never call
the gas company on שבת Shabbos they come and they work on
your gas pipes on שבת, Shabbos, right? So do people are people
like sort of assuming what do people like assuming in those cases
and what falls into this category? So in this big תוספות there's
two big divisions. One division basically says because on the other hand
the famous משנה of בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis
Shammai is that you can like drop off your dry cleaning a
minute before שבת Shabbos? and the non-Jew decides on his own timetable
when to do it. So what's the difference? Okay. So one answer
תוספות gives is the difference between when they take your stuff and
they bring it into their home and do it or their place
of work or are they working on your property? When they're working
on your property right with all these cases, bathhouse, land, etc., it's
much more visible and public and identified with you. If that's true
then there's no היתר Heter for all these cases I just gave
you about the about the plumbing and about the gas and all
those types I mean סכנת נפשות Sakanas Nefashos would be a different
story. But anyway right? So that's one big way of dividing between
what's allowed and what's not allowed. The other way says תוספות has
to do with how much When do people assume that this is
being done, like exactly this question. When will people interpret this through
the right lens or the wrong lens? When do people assume that
you must have hired them to do it and to do it
on שבת, Shabbos, and when is it likely enough that they will
assume that this was the person sort of was on his own
timetable and he's just deciding to do it on שבת? Shabbos. Like
if you're getting a house built, you usually hire the contractor and
the contractor hires all the workers, right? And you're not דווקא davka
hiring the contractor so that the contractor might be hiring the workers
to work on שבת, Shabbos, but your arrangement is with the contractor
and you just want the house finished by a certain time. You're
not telling the contractor he has to work on שבת. Shabbos. So
if people enough understand that reality, that's enough of a reasonable possibility,
then that's the interpretation that people will give it. They see this
contractor work on my house on שבת, Shabbos. what shall they say?
Yeah, Dov has arranged to get his house built and this is
when the contractor's deciding to work on שבת. Shabbos. Dov didn't tell
him to build it on שבת. Shabbos, Okay, so opposed to the
bathhouse, as opposed to the bathhouse, people, that's what the גמרא says,
it's not common enough that you rent it out. It's the standard
is you hire workers and you're getting all the profits, right? And
therefore, people will just assume I'm operating my business on שבת. Shabbos,
So if you look at תוספות, תוספות starts, we'll just do the
first and the last line of תוספות. אריסא. Arisa. תוספות says: פסק
רבנו תם הלכה כרבי שמעון בן גמליאל דאמר אריסא אריסותיה קעביד. pasken
Rabbeinu Tam halacha k'Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel, d'amar arisa arisusei k'avid. Okay,
that as long as you can interpret it that he's, you know,
that it's an אריסות arisus contract, like it's not that they're doing
it on their own timetable, it's okay, and that's how people will
interpret it. ומתוך כך התיר לישראל שהן שנתן ביתו לעשותו בקבלנות לבנות
בו אפילו בשבת. Umitoch kach hitir l'Yisrael she'hein shenasan beiso la'asoso bekablanus
livnos bo afilu beShabbos. Exactly this. You basically gave a non-Jew your
contract to build your house בקבלנות, bekablanus, meaning you're paying him for
the whole deal, you're not hiring him day-by-day, okay, and so he
says and he allowed it, okay, because people understand that that's the
nature of the arrangement. And now if you skip to the very
end, he says that even though this is what רבנו תם Rabbeinu
Tam פסק, paskened, you see the line that starts with the word
אריסותיה, arisutei, it's about twelve lines from the bottom of the דף.
daf. So אריסותיה קעביד, arisutei k'avid, he says, ורבנו תם אף על
פי שהקל בקיבולת, veRabbeinu Tam af al pi shehikil b'kibollet, even though
he technically allowed it when it was contracted out, the building of
a house and not paid by daily labor, החמיר על עצמו, hechmir
al atzmo, for himself he wouldn't do it. וכשבנה ביתו, Ukeshebanah beiso,
when he was getting his own house built, great, you get here,
like רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam getting his house built, לא הניח עובדי
כוכבים לבנות בשבת, lo hinniach ovdei kochavim livnos beShabbos, he didn't allow
it, okay, on שבת, Shabbos? אף על פי שהיו עושים בקבלנות, af
al pi shehayu osim bekablanus, even though they were doing it like
a type of a contractor. Okay, and then anyway, so this whole
תוספות is working out when are the ways in which you can
have a non-Jew, even though technically you're not telling him to work
on שבת, Shabbos, he's making his own decisions, but when does it
look to everybody like you're publicly having him work for you on
שבת? And one's major distinction between land, on your landed property versus
something he's doing in his own, right, and also the issue here
about what do you call it, about a new, about how much
is the interpretation that people give it that you hired this person
to work on שבת, and how much is the interpretation that this,
no, this is just the timetable, this person's working out his own
timetable, you just gave him the job of some sort, okay, so
we will pick up with this on tomorrow.